For me, this story begins about 15 years ago,
بالنسبة لي، تبدأ هذه القصة قبل حوالي 15 عاماً مضت،
when I was a hospice doctor at the University of Chicago.
عندما كنت طبيباً نزيلاً في جامعة شيكاغو.
And I was taking care of people who were dying and their families
وكنت أعتني بالناس الذين على وشك الموت، وأسرهم،
in the South Side of Chicago.
في الجانب الجنوبي لشيكاغو.
And I was observing what happened to people and their families
وكنت أراقب ما يحدث للناس وأسرهم
over the course of their terminal illness.
خلال فترة مرضهم اللأخير.
And in my lab, I was studying the widower effect,
وفي مختبري، كنت أدرس تأثير الأرمل،
which is a very old idea in the social sciences,
الذي هو فكرة قديمة جداً في العلوم الإجتماعية،
going back 150 years,
ترجع لقبل 150 عاماً،
known as "dying of a broken heart."
ومعروفة ب " الموت بسبب إنكسار القلب." "الحزن"
So, when I die, my wife's risk of death can double,
لذا، فحينما أموت، تتضاعف مخاطر موت زوجتي ،
for instance, in the first year.
على سبيل المثال، في العام الأول.
And I had gone to take care of one particular patient,
وقد شاركت في العناية بمريض محدد،
a woman who was dying of dementia.
إمرأة كانت تموت بسبب الجنون.
And in this case, unlike this couple,
وفي هذه الحالة، خلافاً لهذين الزوجين،
she was being cared for
كانت تعتني بها
by her daughter.
بنتها.
And the daughter was exhausted from caring for her mother.
وكانت الإبنة مرهقة من العناية بأمها.
And the daughter's husband,
وكان زوج الإبنة
he also was sick
كذلك قد تعب
from his wife's exhaustion.
من إرهاق زوجته.
And I was driving home one day,
وكنت أقود السيارة إلى المنزل في أحد الأيام،
and I get a phone call from the husband's friend,
وتلقيت مكالمة من صديق الزوج،
calling me because he was depressed
إتصل بي لأنه كان محبطاً
about what was happening to his friend.
لما يجري لصديقه.
So here I get this call from this random guy
إذاً هنا تلقيت هذا الإتصال من شخص عشوائي
that's having an experience
الذي يمر بتجربة،
that's being influenced by people
يتحكم فيها أناس
at some social distance.
على مسافة إجتماعية.
And so I suddenly realized two very simple things:
ولذا فقد أدركت فجأة شيئين بسيطين للغاية.
First, the widowhood effect
أولاً، تأثير الأرمل
was not restricted to husbands and wives.
لم يكن قاصراً على الأزواج و الزوجات.
And second, it was not restricted to pairs of people.
وثانياً، لم يكن قاصراً على زوجين من الناس.
And I started to see the world
وبدأت أرى العالم
in a whole new way,
بطريقة مختلفة كلياً،
like pairs of people connected to each other.
مثل زوجين من الناس موصولين ببعضهما البعض.
And then I realized that these individuals
ثم أدركت أن هؤلاء الأفراد
would be connected into foursomes with other pairs of people nearby.
سيصبحوا في رباعي مع زوجين آخرين من الناس القريبين.
And then, in fact, these people
ثم، في الواقع هؤلاء الناس
were embedded in other sorts of relationships:
كانوا جزءاً أصيلاً في أنواع أخرى من العلاقات،
marriage and spousal
الزواج والنسب
and friendship and other sorts of ties.
والصداقة وأنواع أخرى من الروابط.
And that, in fact, these connections were vast
وأنه في الحقيقة، هذه الوصلات كانت شاسعة،
and that we were all embedded in this
وأننا جميعاً جزء لا يتجزأ في هذه
broad set of connections with each other.
المجموعة الواسعة من الوصلات مع بعضنا البعض.
So I started to see the world in a completely new way
لذا فقد بدأت أرى العالم بطريقة جديدة كلياً،
and I became obsessed with this.
وأصبحت مهووساً بهذا.
I became obsessed with how it might be
وأصبحت مهووسا بكيف أننا قد نكون
that we're embedded in these social networks,
جزء من هذه الشبكات الإجتماعية،
and how they affect our lives.
وكيف أنها تؤثر في حياتنا.
So, social networks are these intricate things of beauty,
إذاً، فالشبكات الإجتماعية هي تلك الأمور المعقدة الجمال،
and they're so elaborate and so complex
وهي دقيقة جداً ومعقدة
and so ubiquitous, in fact,
وشاملة جداً ، في الواقع،
that one has to ask what purpose they serve.
بحيث ينبغي على الشخص السؤال عن أي هدف تخدمه.
Why are we embedded in social networks?
لماذا نحن موجودين في شبكات إجتماعية؟
I mean, how do they form? How do they operate?
أعني، كيف تتشكل؟ وكيف تعمل؟
And how do they effect us?
وكيف تقوم بالتأثير علينا؟
So my first topic with respect to this,
ولذا فأول موضوعاتي، فيما يتعلق بهذا،
was not death, but obesity.
ليس عن الموت، لكن عن السُمنة.
It had become trendy
وفجأة، لقد أصبحت موضة شائعة
to speak about the "obesity epidemic."
التحدث عن وباء السُمنة.
And, along with my collaborator, James Fowler,
وبالتعاون مع شريكي، جيمس فولر،
we began to wonder whether obesity really was epidemic
بدأنا الإستغراب حول سواء كانت السُمنة بالفعل وباءً،
and could it spread from person to person
ويمكن أن تنتقل من شخص لآخر
like the four people I discussed earlier.
مثل الأربعة أشخاص الذين ناقشتهم باكراً.
So this is a slide of some of our initial results.
لذا فهذه الشريحة لبعض النتائج الأولية.
It's 2,200 people in the year 2000.
إنهم 2200 شخص في العام 2000.
Every dot is a person. We make the dot size
كل نقطة تمثل شخص. ونجعل حجم النقطة
proportional to people's body size;
متناسباً مع حجم الشخص.
so bigger dots are bigger people.
لذا فالنقاط الأكبر تمثل أشخاص أكبر في الحجم.
In addition, if your body size,
إضافة لذلك، إن كان حجم جسمك،
if your BMI, your body mass index, is above 30 --
إن كان مؤشر كتلة جسمك أعلى من 30،
if you're clinically obese --
إن كنت سميناً سريرياً،
we also colored the dots yellow.
قمنا بتلوين النقاط باللون الأصفر.
So, if you look at this image, right away you might be able to see
لذا، إذا نظرتم لهذه الصورة على الفور، قد يمكنكم رؤية
that there are clusters of obese and
أن هناك ثلاث مجموعات من الناس السمان و
non-obese people in the image.
غير السمان في هذه الصورة.
But the visual complexity is still very high.
لكن التعقيد المرئي ما يزال هائلاً للغاية.
It's not obvious exactly what's going on.
وليس واضحاً بالضبط ما الذي يجري.
In addition, some questions are immediately raised:
إضافةً، يبرز في الحال بعض الأسئلة.
How much clustering is there?
كم مجموعة موجودة هناك؟
Is there more clustering than would be due to chance alone?
هل هناك مجموعات أكثر ستكون بسبب الصدفة وحدها؟
How big are the clusters? How far do they reach?
ما هو كبر المجموعات؟ كم سيصل بُعدها؟
And, most importantly,
والأهم من كل ذلك،
what causes the clusters?
ما الذي يتسبب في إنشاء المجموعات؟
So we did some mathematics to study the size of these clusters.
لذا فقد قمنا ببعض الحسابات لدراسة حجم هذه المجموعات.
This here shows, on the Y-axis,
وهذا هنا يبيّن، على المحور الصادي،
the increase in the probability that a person is obese
زيادة إحتمال أن شخص سمين،
given that a social contact of theirs is obese
علماً بأن شخص في قائمتهم مصاب بالسُمنة.
and, on the X-axis, the degrees of separation between the two people.
وعلى المحور السيني، درجة الإنفصال ما بين الشخصين.
On the far left, you see the purple line.
وعلى أقصى اليسار، ترى الخط البنفسجي.
It says that, if your friends are obese,
وينص على أن، إذا كان أصدقائك مصابين بالسُمنة،
your risk of obesity is 45 percent higher.
فان مخاطر الإصابة بالسُمنة أعلى بنسبة 45%.
And the next bar over, the [red] line,
والخط الثاني هناك، الخط البرتقالي،
says if your friend's friends are obese,
ينص على، إذا كان صديق صديقك مصاب بالسُمنة،
your risk of obesity is 25 percent higher.
فان مخاطر الإصابة أعلى بنسبة 25%.
And then the next line over says
والخط التالي له ينص على،
if your friend's friend's friend, someone you probably don't even know, is obese,
إذا كان صديق صديق صديقك، شخص ما على الأرجح لا تعرفه حتى، مصاب بالسُمنة،
your risk of obesity is 10 percent higher.
فان مخاطر إصابتك أعلى بنسبة 10%.
And it's only when you get to your friend's friend's friend's friends
فقط حينما يصل الأمر لصديق صديق صديق صديقك،
that there's no longer a relationship
لم تعد هناك علاقة
between that person's body size and your own body size.
بين حجم جسم الشخص وحجم جسمك.
Well, what might be causing this clustering?
حسناً، ما الذي يتسبب في هذه المجموعات؟
There are at least three possibilities:
هناك على الأقل ثلاث إحتمالات.
One possibility is that, as I gain weight,
أولاً، إحتمال أنه، بينما أكتسب انا الوزن،
it causes you to gain weight.
يتسبب ذلك في إكتسابك للوزن،
A kind of induction, a kind of spread from person to person.
كنوع من التقليد ، نوع من الإنتقال من شخص لآخر.
Another possibility, very obvious, is homophily,
إحتمال آخر، واضح جداً، وهو الخوف من الوحدة،
or, birds of a feather flock together;
أو الطيور على أشكالها تقع.
here, I form my tie to you
هنا، أقوم بتشكيل علاقتي بك
because you and I share a similar body size.
لأننا نتشارك في حجم جسم متقارب.
And the last possibility is what is known as confounding,
والإحتمال الأخير هو ما يُعرف بالإلتباس،
because it confounds our ability to figure out what's going on.
لأنها يفند قدرتنا على معرفة ما يجري.
And here, the idea is not that my weight gain
وهنا، الفكرة ليست أن إكتسابي للوزن
is causing your weight gain,
يتسبب في أن تكتسب أنت الوزن،
nor that I preferentially form a tie with you
ولا أنني أفضل تشكيل رابط بيننا
because you and I share the same body size,
لأننا نتشارك نفس حجم الجسم ،
but rather that we share a common exposure
لكن عوضاً عن ذلك نحن نتعرض لنفس الشئ معا
to something, like a health club
لشئ مثل النادي الرياضي
that makes us both lose weight at the same time.
الذي يجعلنا سوياً نفقد الوزن في نفس الوقت.
When we studied these data, we found evidence for all of these things,
وعندما درسنا هذه البيانات، وجدنا دليلاً لكل هذه الأشياء،
including for induction.
وضمنها التقليد.
And we found that if your friend becomes obese,
وقد وجدنا أنه، إذا كان صديقك يصبح سميناً،
it increases your risk of obesity by about 57 percent
فان ذلك يرفع من مخاطر إصابتك بالسمنة لحوالي 57%
in the same given time period.
في نفس الفترة الزمنية.
There can be many mechanisms for this effect:
وقد يكون هناك الكثير من الآليات لهذا التأثير.
One possibility is that your friends say to you something like --
أحد الإحتمالات هو أن يقول لك أصدقائك شيئاً مثل --
you know, they adopt a behavior that spreads to you --
كما تعلمون، يقومون بتبني السلوك الذي ينتقل إليك،
like, they say, "Let's go have muffins and beer,"
مثل، " لنذهب لأكل الكعك وشرب البيرة،"
which is a terrible combination. (Laughter)
التي هي مزيج فظيع،
But you adopt that combination,
لكنك تتماشى مع ذلك المزيج،
and then you start gaining weight like them.
وتبدأ في إكتساب الوزن مثلهم.
Another more subtle possibility
وإحتمال آخر أكثر دقة
is that they start gaining weight, and it changes your ideas
هو أن تبدأ في إكتساب الوزن، ويتسبب في تغيير أفكارك
of what an acceptable body size is.
حول ماهية حجم الجسم المقبول.
Here, what's spreading from person to person
وهنا، الشئ الذي ينتقل من شخص لآخر
is not a behavior, but rather a norm:
ليس هو السلوك، بل العادة.
An idea is spreading.
فكرة تنتشر.
Now, headline writers
الآن، كُتّاب العناوين الرئيسية
had a field day with our studies.
لديهم عمل يومي ميداني مع دراساتنا.
I think the headline in The New York Times was,
أعتقد أن العنوان الرئيسي في صحيفة النيويورك تايمز كان،
"Are you packing it on?
"هل أنت منتفخ (سمين)؟
Blame your fat friends." (Laughter)
عليك بلوم صديقك السمين."
What was interesting to us is that the European headline writers
ما كان مثيراً بالنسبة لنا هو عناوين الصحف الأوروبية
had a different take: They said,
التي أخذت الأمر بصورة مختلفة، مثل،
"Are your friends gaining weight? Perhaps you are to blame."
" هل يكتسب صديقك الوزن؟ ربما أنت السبب."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And we thought this was a very interesting comment on America,
وقد فكرنا بأن هذا تعليق مثير للغاية في أمريكا،
and a kind of self-serving,
نوع من خدمة الذات،
"not my responsibility" kind of phenomenon.
نوع من ، " ليست مسئوليتي" نوع من الظواهر.
Now, I want to be very clear: We do not think our work
الآن أريد أن أكون واضحاً، نحن لا نعتقد أن عملنا
should or could justify prejudice
ينبغي أو يمكن أن يبرر الأحكام المسبقة
against people of one or another body size at all.
ضد الناس من شخص لآخر حول أحجام أجسامهم بتاتاً.
Our next questions was:
وكان سؤالنا التالي هو:
Could we actually visualize this spread?
هل يمكننا جعل هذا الإنتشار مرئياً؟
Was weight gain in one person actually spreading
هل زيادة الوزن عند شخص تنتشر حقيقةً
to weight gain in another person?
لتصبح زيادة وزن لشخص آخر؟
And this was complicated because
وكان هذا معقداً بسبب
we needed to take into account the fact that the network structure,
أننا أحتجنا أن نأخذ في إعتبارنا حقيقة أن شكل الشبكة،
the architecture of the ties, was changing across time.
وبنية العلاقات ، تتغيران عبر الزمن.
In addition, because obesity is not a unicentric epidemic,
بالإضافة، لأن السُمنة ليست وباء مركزياً،
there's not a Patient Zero of the obesity epidemic --
لا يوجد هناك "المريض الأول" لوباء السمنة--
if we find that guy, there was a spread of obesity out from him --
فتجد أن شخصا مت كانت بداية إنتشار السمنة من عنده.
it's a multicentric epidemic.
إنها وباء متعدد المراكز.
Lots of people are doing things at the same time.
الكثير من الناس يفعلون أشياء في نفس الوقت.
And I'm about to show you a 30 second video animation
وأنا على وشك عرض فيديو رسومي طوله 30 ثانية
that took me and James five years of our lives to do.
الذي أستغرق منا بناءه أنا وجيمس خمسة سنوات.
So, again, every dot is a person.
ولذا، مجدداً، كل نقطة تمثل شخص.
Every tie between them is a relationship.
كل رابط بينهما يمثل علاقة.
We're going to put this into motion now,
وسنقوم بوضع هذا قيد التشغيل الآن،
taking daily cuts through the network for about 30 years.
آخذين قطوعات يومية للشبكة لحوالي 30 عاماً.
The dot sizes are going to grow,
حجم النقاط سيبدأ في النمو.
you're going to see a sea of yellow take over.
سترون بحر من اللون الأصفر يبدأ في التشكل.
You're going to see people be born and die --
سترون أناس يولودون ويموتون.
dots will appear and disappear --
ستظهر النقاط وتختفي.
ties will form and break, marriages and divorces,
ستتشكل الروابط وتتكسر. زيجات وطلاقات،
friendings and defriendings.
إقامة علاقات وإنهائها،
A lot of complexity, a lot is happening
الكثير من التعقيد، الكثير يحدث
just in this 30-year period
فقط في فترة ثلاثين عاماً،
that includes the obesity epidemic.
ويشمل ذلك وباء السُمنة.
And, by the end, you're going to see clusters
وبالوصول للنهاية، ستشاهدون مجموعات
of obese and non-obese individuals
من المصابين بالسُمنة وغير المصابين بها
within the network.
داخل الشبكة.
Now, when looked at this,
الآن، حين النظر لهذا،
it changed the way I see things,
لقد غيرت الطريقة التي أرى بها الأشياء،
because this thing, this network
لأن هذا الشئ، هذه الشبكة،
that's changing across time,
التي تتغير مع مرور الزمن،
it has a memory, it moves,
لديها ذاكرة، إنها تنتقل،
things flow within it,
تدخل عليها أشياء،
it has a kind of consistency --
ولديها نوع من الإتساق.
people can die, but it doesn't die;
يمكن أن يموت الناس، لكنها لا تموت.
it still persists --
بل لا تزال مستمرة.
and it has a kind of resilience
ولها نوع من المرونة
that allows it to persist across time.
التي تسمح بإستمراريتها عبر الزمن.
And so, I came to see these kinds of social networks
ولذا، فقد توصلت لرؤية هذه العلامات للشبكات الإجتماعية
as living things,
كعناصر حية،
as living things that we could put under a kind of microscope
كعناصر حية بمستطاعنا وضعها تحت المجهر
to study and analyze and understand.
وندرسها ونحللها ونفهمها.
And we used a variety of techniques to do this.
ونحن نستخدم باقة متنوعة من التقنيات لفعل هذا.
And we started exploring all kinds of other phenomena.
وقد بدأنا في إستكشاف كل أنواع الظواهر الأخرى.
We looked at smoking and drinking behavior,
إذاً فقد نظرنا في سلوك المدخنين وشاربي الكحول،
and voting behavior,
وسلوك التصويت "الإنتخابي"،
and divorce -- which can spread --
والطلاق، الذي يمكن أن ينتشر،
and altruism.
والإيثار.
And, eventually, we became interested in emotions.
وفي نهاية المُطاف، أصبحنا مهتمين بالمشاعر.
Now, when we have emotions,
الآن، حينما يكون لدينا مشاعر،
we show them.
نعرب عنها.
Why do we show our emotions?
لماذا نقوم بإظهار مشاعرنا؟
I mean, there would be an advantage to experiencing
أعني، قد يكون هناك ميزة لتجربة
our emotions inside, you know, anger or happiness.
عواطفنا داخلياً، كما تعلمون، الغضب والسعادة،
But we don't just experience them, we show them.
لكننا لا نقوم بعيشها، نحن نظهرها.
And not only do we show them, but others can read them.
وليس فقط نقوم باظهارها، لكن بإمكان الآخرين قراءتها.
And, not only can they read them, but they copy them.
وليس فقط يمكنهم قراءتها، بل يستطيعون نسخها.
There's emotional contagion
هناك عدوى عاطفية
that takes place in human populations.
تحدث في المجتمعات البشرية.
And so this function of emotions
إذاً فمهمة المشاعر هذه
suggests that, in addition to any other purpose they serve,
تقترح أنه، إضافة لأي هدف آخر تقوم بخدمته،
they're a kind of primitive form of communication.
فانها نوع من الأشكال البدائية للتواصل.
And that, in fact, if we really want to understand human emotions,
وذلك في الواقع، إذا أردنا حقاً أن نفهم المشاعر البشرية،
we need to think about them in this way.
فنحن نحتاج للتفكير بهم بهذه الطريقة.
Now, we're accustomed to thinking about emotions in this way,
الآن، نحن تعودنا على التفكير حول المشاعر بهذه الطريقة،
in simple, sort of, brief periods of time.
بطريقة مبسطة ولفترة زمنية قصيرة.
So, for example,
لذا، على سبيل المثال،
I was giving this talk recently in New York City,
كنت أقدم هذا الحديث مؤخراً في مدينة نيويورك،
and I said, "You know when you're on the subway
وقد قلت، " تعلمون، كما لو أنكم في القطار،
and the other person across the subway car
والشخص الجالس قبالتكم في المقطورة
smiles at you,
يبتسم لك،
and you just instinctively smile back?"
وتبتسم له أنت بغريزتك."
And they looked at me and said, "We don't do that in New York City." (Laughter)
وقد نظروا إلى وجهي وقالوا، " نحن لا نفعل ذلك في مدينة نيويورك."
And I said, "Everywhere else in the world,
وقد قلت، " في أي مكان آخر في العالم،
that's normal human behavior."
ذلك هو التصرف الطبيعي للبشر."
And so there's a very instinctive way
ولذا فهناك طريقة غريزية للغاية
in which we briefly transmit emotions to each other.
التي عبرها يتم نقل المشاعر من شخص لآخر.
And, in fact, emotional contagion can be broader still.
وفي الواقع، قد تكون العدوى العاطفية أكبر من ذلك،
Like we could have punctuated expressions of anger,
كما قد يكون لدينا تعبيرات يتخللها الغضب،
as in riots.
كما في أعمال الشغب.
The question that we wanted to ask was:
السؤال الذي أردنا طرحه كان:
Could emotion spread,
هل يمكن للمشاعر أن تنتقل،
in a more sustained way than riots, across time
بطريقة أكثر إستدامة من أعمال الشغب، عبر الزمن
and involve large numbers of people,
وتتضمن عدد مأهول من الناس،
not just this pair of individuals smiling at each other in the subway car?
ليس فقط زوجين من الأفراد يبتسمون لبعض البعض في مقطورة القطار؟
Maybe there's a kind of below the surface, quiet riot
ربما يوجد نوع من أعمال الشغب تحت السطح
that animates us all the time.
التي تحركنا جميعاً.
Maybe there are emotional stampedes
ربما هناك تدافع عاطفي
that ripple through social networks.
يموج عبر الشبكات الإجتماعية.
Maybe, in fact, emotions have a collective existence,
ربما، في الواقع، للمشاعر تواجد جماعي،
not just an individual existence.
ليس فقط تواجد منفرد.
And this is one of the first images we made to study this phenomenon.
وهذه هي أول الصور التي صنعناها لهذه الظاهرة.
Again, a social network,
مرة أخرى، شبكة إجتماعية،
but now we color the people yellow if they're happy
لكننا الآن نقوم بتلوين الناس باللون الأصفر إذا كانوا سعداء
and blue if they're sad and green in between.
وأزرق إن كانوا غاضبين وما بينهما اللون الأخضر.
And if you look at this image, you can right away see
وإذا نظرت في هذه الصورة، يمكنك على الفور رؤية
clusters of happy and unhappy people,
مجموعات من الناس السعداء والغاضبين،
again, spreading to three degrees of separation.
مرة أخرى، تنتشر لثلاث درجات من الإنفصال.
And you might form the intuition
وربما تشكّل لديك فكرة
that the unhappy people
بأن الناس الغاضبين
occupy a different structural location within the network.
يشغلون شكل مساحة مختلفة داخل الشبكة.
There's a middle and an edge to this network,
إذاً فهناك منتصف و حد لهذا الشبكة،
and the unhappy people seem to be
ويبدو أن الناس الغاضبين
located at the edges.
يقعون في الحواف.
So to invoke another metaphor,
إذاً لإستدعاء إستعارة أخرى،
if you imagine social networks as a kind of
إن تخيلتم الشبكة الإجتماعية كنوع من
vast fabric of humanity --
النسيج الهائل للبشرية--
I'm connected to you and you to her, on out endlessly into the distance --
أنا متصل بك وبها، لمسافة تمتد لمالانهاية--
this fabric is actually like
هذا النسيج في الواقع مثل
an old-fashioned American quilt,
لحاف أمريكي من الطراز القديم،
and it has patches on it: happy and unhappy patches.
وعليه بُقع، بقع سعيدة وبقع حزينة.
And whether you become happy or not
وسواء كنت سعيد أم لا
depends in part on whether you occupy a happy patch.
يعتمد جزئيا على إذا كنت تشغل بقعة سعيدة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So, this work with emotions,
إذاً، هذا العمل مع المشاعر،
which are so fundamental,
الذي هو أساسي جداً،
then got us to thinking about: Maybe
أخذنا بعد ذلك للتفكير حول، ربما
the fundamental causes of human social networks
الأسباب الأساسية التي تشكل الشبكات الإجتماعية البشرية
are somehow encoded in our genes.
هي بطريقة ما مكتوبة في جيناتنا.
Because human social networks, whenever they are mapped,
لأن الشبكات الإجتماعية البشرية، في أي وقت تم تخطيطها،
always kind of look like this:
دائماً تظهر شيئاً كهذا،
the picture of the network.
صورة شكل الشبكة،
But they never look like this.
لكنها لا تظهر هكذا مطلقاً.
Why do they not look like this?
لماذا تبدو هكذا؟
Why don't we form human social networks
لم لا نشكّل شبكات إجتماعية بشرية
that look like a regular lattice?
تظهر بشكل الشبكات المعتادة؟
Well, the striking patterns of human social networks,
حسناً، الأنماط المدهشة لشبكات البشر الإجتماعية،
their ubiquity and their apparent purpose
إنتشارها، وهدفها الواضح
beg questions about whether we evolved to have
يطرح سؤالاً حول سواء كنا قد تطورنا لنحصل
human social networks in the first place,
على شبكات إجتماعية بشرية من البداية،
and whether we evolved to form networks
أو أننا قدد تطورنا لنشكّل شبكات
with a particular structure.
على شاكلة محددة.
And notice first of all -- so, to understand this, though,
ثم لاحظوا قبل كل شئ...لنفهم هذا،
we need to dissect network structure a little bit first --
فنحن نحتاج لتشريح بنية الشبكة قليلاً.
and notice that every person in this network
لاحظوا ان لدى كل شخص في هذه الشبكة
has exactly the same structural location as every other person.
نفس الموقع الهيكلي بالضبط كأي شخص آخر.
But that's not the case with real networks.
لكن ذلك ليس هو الحال مع الشبكات الحقيقية.
So, for example, here is a real network of college students
لذا، على سبيل المثال، ها هي شبكة حقيقية لطلاب جامعة
at an elite northeastern university.
لنخبة في جامعة الشمال الشرقي.
And now I'm highlighting a few dots.
والآن أقوم بتسليط الضوء على نقاط قليلة.
If you look here at the dots,
وإذا نظرتم لهذه النقاط،
compare node B in the upper left
قارنتم تقاطع "ب"، في اليسار لأعلى،
to node D in the far right;
مع تقاطع "د" في أقصى اليمين.
B has four friends coming out from him
ولدى "ب" أربعة أصدقاء يخرجون منه.
and D has six friends coming out from him.
ولدى "د" ست أصدقاء يخرجون منه.
And so, those two individuals have different numbers of friends.
ولذا، لهذين الشخصين عدد مختلف من الأصدقاء--
That's very obvious, we all know that.
ذلك واضح جداً، جميعنا يعرف ذلك.
But certain other aspects
لكن جوانب أخرى
of social network structure are not so obvious.
لبنية الشبكة الإجتماعية ليست واضحة جداً.
Compare node B in the upper left to node A in the lower left.
قارنوا تقاطع "ب" في أعلى اليسار مع تقاطع "أ" في أسفل اليسار.
Now, those people both have four friends,
والآن كلٌ من هذين الشخصين لديه أربعة أصدقاء،
but A's friends all know each other,
لكن جميع أصدقاء "أ" يعرفون بعضهم البعض،
and B's friends do not.
لكن أصدقاء "ب" ليسوا كذلك.
So the friend of a friend of A's
إذاً فصديق صديق "أ"،
is, back again, a friend of A's,
يرجع مرة أخرى صديقاً ل "أ"،
whereas the friend of a friend of B's is not a friend of B's,
في حين صديق صديق "ب" ليس صديقاً ل"ب"،
but is farther away in the network.
وهو أبعد بكثير في الشبكة.
This is known as transitivity in networks.
يعرف هذا بالتعدي في الشبكات.
And, finally, compare nodes C and D:
وأخيراً، قارنوا تقاطع "س" و"د".
C and D both have six friends.
لكل من "س" و"د" ست أصدقاء.
If you talk to them, and you said, "What is your social life like?"
إذا تحدثت إليهم، وقلت، " كيف تبدو علاقاتك الإجتماعية؟"
they would say, "I've got six friends.
سيقولون، " لدي ست أصدقاء.
That's my social experience."
ذلك هو تواصلي الإجتماعي."
But now we, with a bird's eye view looking at this network,
لكن الآن بنظرة طائرة على هذه الشبكة،
can see that they occupy very different social worlds.
يمكن رؤية أنهم يشغلون عوالم إجتماعية مختلفة،
And I can cultivate that intuition in you by just asking you:
ويمكنني زرع تلك الفكرة داخلكم بسؤالكم:
Who would you rather be
من ستختار أن تكون
if a deadly germ was spreading through the network?
إذا كانت هناك جرثومة قاتلة تنتشر عبر الشبكة؟
Would you rather be C or D?
هل ترغب في أن تكون "س" أو "د"؟
You'd rather be D, on the edge of the network.
ستفضل أن تكون "د"، على حافة الشبكة.
And now who would you rather be
والآن من ستختار أن تكون
if a juicy piece of gossip -- not about you --
إذا كانت هناك نميمة طريفة، ليس عنك،
was spreading through the network? (Laughter)
كانت تنتشر عبر الشبكة؟
Now, you would rather be C.
الآن، ستفضل أن تكون "س".
So different structural locations
إذاً للمواقع التكوينية المختلفة
have different implications for your life.
تأثيرات مختلفة على حياتك.
And, in fact, when we did some experiments looking at this,
وفي الواقع، عندما قمنا ببعض التجارب في النظر لهذا،
what we found is that 46 percent of the variation
ما وجدناه هو أن 46% من التباين
in how many friends you have
حول كم صديق لديك
is explained by your genes.
يفسّر بواسطة جيناتك.
And this is not surprising. We know that some people are born shy
وهذا ليس مستغرباً. نحن نعرف، أن بعض الناس يولدون خجولين
and some are born gregarious. That's obvious.
وبعضهم يولد إجتماعي. وهذا واضح.
But we also found some non-obvious things.
لكننا وجدناً أيضاً بعض الأشياء غير الواضحة.
For instance, 47 percent in the variation
على سبيل المثال، 47% في التباين
in whether your friends know each other
في سواء كان أصدقائك يعرفون بعضهم البعض
is attributable to your genes.
يعود للجينات الخاصة بك.
Whether your friends know each other
سواء عرف أصدقائك بعضهم البعض
has not just to do with their genes, but with yours.
لا يتعلق فقط بجيناتهم، بل بجيناتك أنت.
And we think the reason for this is that some people
ونحن نعتقد أن السبب وراء هذا هو أن بعض الناس
like to introduce their friends to each other -- you know who you are --
يحبون تقديم أصدقائهم لبعضهم البعض، يعرفون من تكون،
and others of you keep them apart and don't introduce your friends to each other.
وغيرهم يقومون بابعادهم عن بعض ولا يقدمون أصدقائهم لبعضهم البعض.
And so some people knit together the networks around them,
ولذا يربط بعض الناس الشبكات التي تحيط بهم،
creating a kind of dense web of ties
صانعين نوع من الشبكة الكثيفة من الروابط
in which they're comfortably embedded.
التي يكونوا مرتاحين فيها .
And finally, we even found that
وحتى أننا وجدنا أنه
30 percent of the variation
30% من التباين
in whether or not people are in the middle or on the edge of the network
حول إذا ما كان بمقدورنا ربط الناس
can also be attributed to their genes.
في منتصف أو حدود الشبكة بجيناتهم.
So whether you find yourself in the middle or on the edge
إذاً سواء وجدت نفسك في المنتصف أو على الحافة،
is also partially heritable.
فذلك ايضاً موروث جيني في جانب منه.
Now, what is the point of this?
الآن، ماهي خلاصة هذا؟
How does this help us understand?
كيف يساعدنا هذا على الفهم؟
How does this help us
كيف يساعدنا هذا
figure out some of the problems that are affecting us these days?
لمعرفة حلول لبعض المشاكل التي تؤثر علينا هذه الأيام؟
Well, the argument I'd like to make is that networks have value.
حسناً، النقاش الذي أرغب في طرحه هو أن للشبكات قيمة.
They are a kind of social capital.
فهي نوع من رأس المال الإجتماعي.
New properties emerge
تظهر أنواع جديدة من الخصائص
because of our embeddedness in social networks,
بسبب ضلوعنا في الشبكات الإجتماعية،
and these properties inhere
وهذه الخصائص هنا،
in the structure of the networks,
في بنية الشبكات،
not just in the individuals within them.
ليست فقط أفراد بداخلها.
So think about these two common objects.
لذا فكروا بهذين الشيئين المعروفين.
They're both made of carbon,
كلاهما مصنوع من الكربون،
and yet one of them has carbon atoms in it
لكن جزيئات الكربون في أحدهما
that are arranged in one particular way -- on the left --
مرتبة بطريقة محددة، على اليسار،
and you get graphite, which is soft and dark.
وتحصل على الغرافايت، الذي هو أملس وداكن.
But if you take the same carbon atoms
لكن إذا أخذت نفس جزيئات الكربون
and interconnect them a different way,
وربطتها بطريقة مختلفة،
you get diamond, which is clear and hard.
ستحصل على المأس، الذي هو نقي وصلب.
And those properties of softness and hardness and darkness and clearness
وتلك الخواص لليونة والصلابة والداكن والنقي
do not reside in the carbon atoms;
لا تقبع في ذرات الكربون.
they reside in the interconnections between the carbon atoms,
إنها تقبع في التشابك ما بين ذرات الكربون،
or at least arise because of the
أو على الأقل تظهر بسبب
interconnections between the carbon atoms.
التشابك بين ذرات الكربون.
So, similarly, the pattern of connections among people
إذاً ، وبالمثل، فانماط التشابك بين البشر
confers upon the groups of people
يضفي على مجموعات الناس
different properties.
خصائص مختلفة.
It is the ties between people
إنها الروابط بين الناس
that makes the whole greater than the sum of its parts.
التي تجعل الكل أعظم من مجموع أجزاءه.
And so it is not just what's happening to these people --
ولذا فالأمر ليس فقط ما يحدث لهؤلاء الناس،
whether they're losing weight or gaining weight, or becoming rich or becoming poor,
سواء كانوا يفقدون الوزن أو يتسكبوه، أو يصبحون أثرياء أو فقراء،
or becoming happy or not becoming happy -- that affects us;
أو يصبحون سعداء أو غير سعداء، يؤثر علينا ذلك .
it's also the actual architecture
إنها كذلك البنية الحقيقية
of the ties around us.
للروابط من حولنا.
Our experience of the world
تجربنا للعالم
depends on the actual structure
تعتمد على البنية الحقيقية
of the networks in which we're residing
للشبكات التي نقع ضمنها
and on all the kinds of things that ripple and flow
وعلى نوع الأشياء التي تتموج وتنساب
through the network.
عبر الشبكة.
Now, the reason, I think, that this is the case
الآن، السبب، كما أعتقد، أن هذا الوضع
is that human beings assemble themselves
هو أن البشر يجمّعون أنفسهم
and form a kind of superorganism.
ويشكلون نوع من الكائنات الحية الضخمة.
Now, a superorganism is a collection of individuals
الآن، الكائنات الحية الضخمة هي نوع من مجموعة من الأفراد
which show or evince behaviors or phenomena
التي تظهر أو تبدي سلوك أو ظواهر
that are not reducible to the study of individuals
التي لا تتقلص لدراسة الأفراد
and that must be understood by reference to,
ويجب أن يتم دراستها بالإشارة إلى ،
and by studying, the collective.
وبدراسة المجموع،
Like, for example, a hive of bees
مثل، خلية النحل
that's finding a new nesting site,
التي تجد مكان جديد للعيش،
or a flock of birds that's evading a predator,
أو سرب من الطيور التي تهرب من حيوان مفترس،
or a flock of birds that's able to pool its wisdom
أو سرب من الطيور القادرة على التجمع بحكمة
and navigate and find a tiny speck
وتستكشف وتجد بقعة صغيرة
of an island in the middle of the Pacific,
لجزيرة في وسط المحيط الهادئ،
or a pack of wolves that's able
أو مجموعة من الذئاب القادرة على
to bring down larger prey.
إسقاط أكبر عدد من الفرائس.
Superorganisms have properties
للكائنات الحية الضخمة خصائص
that cannot be understood just by studying the individuals.
لا يمكن فهمها بدراسة الأفراد فقط.
I think understanding social networks
أعتقد أن فهم الشبكات الإجتماعية
and how they form and operate
وكيف تتشكل وتعمل،
can help us understand not just health and emotions
يمكن أن يساعدنا، ليس فقط في الصحة والمشاعر،
but all kinds of other phenomena --
بل لكل أنواع الظواهر
like crime, and warfare,
مثل الجريمة والرفاهية
and economic phenomena like bank runs
والظواهر الإقتصادية مثل إفلاس البنك
and market crashes
وإنهيار الأسواق
and the adoption of innovation
وتبني الإبتكار
and the spread of product adoption.
وإنتشار تبني المنتجات "شراؤها".
Now, look at this.
الآن، أنظروا لهذا.
I think we form social networks
أعتقد أننا نشكّل الشبكات الإجتماعية
because the benefits of a connected life
لأننا نستفيد من التواصل الحياتي
outweigh the costs.
الذي يفوق التكاليف.
If I was always violent towards you
وإذا كنت دائم العنف تجاهك
or gave you misinformation
أو أعطيتك معلومات خاطئة،
or made you sad or infected you with deadly germs,
أو تسببت في حزنك، أو مصاب معك بجرثومة قاتلة،
you would cut the ties to me,
فستقوم بقطع روابط معي،
and the network would disintegrate.
ولن تتكامل الشبكة.
So the spread of good and valuable things
إذاً فانتشار الأشياء القيّمة والجيدة
is required to sustain and nourish social networks.
مطلوب لإستدامة ودعم الشبكات الإجتماعية.
Similarly, social networks are required
بالمثل، الشبكات الإجتماعية مطلوبة
for the spread of good and valuable things,
لإنتشار الأشياء الجيدة والقيّمة
like love and kindness
مثل الحب والعطف
and happiness and altruism
والسعادة و الإيثار
and ideas.
والأفكار.
I think, in fact, that if we realized
أعتقد، في الحقيقة، أننا إذا أدركنا
how valuable social networks are,
كم الشبكات الإجتماعية قيّمة،
we'd spend a lot more time nourishing them and sustaining them,
فسنقضي وقتاً أكثر في دعمها وإستدامتها
because I think social networks
لأنني أعتقد أن الشبكات الإجتماعية
are fundamentally related to goodness.
مرتبطة في الأساس بالخير،
And what I think the world needs now
وما أعتقد أن العالم بحاجة إليه الآن
is more connections.
هو تواصل أكثر.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)